## Rafael Massahiro Yassue

E-mail: rafael.yassue@usp.br

Website: https://rafaelyassue.github.io/cv-online/Git-Hub: https://github.com/RafaelYassue/ORCID: http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7424-2227

g/0000-0002-7424-2227

I am a Ph.D. candidate with experience in plant breeding, field experimentation, quantitative genetics, statistical modeling, phenomics, and genomics. My line of research is connecting genomics, high-throughput phenotyping, machine learning, and plant growth-promoting bacteria to plant breeding. My goal is to solve challenges by applying multidisciplinary approaches. Furthermore, I continuously improve myself in communication, teamwork, and leadership.

#### Education

- 2018: Ph.D. (in progress), Genetics and Plant Breeding, Luiz de Queiroz College of Agriculture University of São Paulo, SP, Brazil
  - ✓ Dissertation: "Genetic architecture of tropical maize for interaction with plant growth-promoting bacteria via high-throughput phenotyping"
    - ✓ Advisor: Prof. Dr. Roberto Fritsche-Neto
- 2016-2018: M.S., Genetics and Plant Breeding, Luiz de Queiroz College of Agriculture University of São Paulo SP, Brazil
  - Thesis: "Tolerance of soybean to Asian rust in multivariate diallel and contrasting environments of fungicides"
    - ✓ Advisor: Prof. Dr. Natal Antonio Vello
  - 2011-2015: B.Sc. Agronomic Engineering. Western Paraná State University, PR, Brazil

# Experience

- 2016-2019: Member of plant breeding study group, GVENCK
  - ✔ Organizing scientific events, promote discussions on relevant genetic and plant breeding issues, and soft skills improvement
- 2015: Academic internship, Soybean breeding, ESALQ
  - ✓ Field experimentation, scientific discussion, and data analysis
- 2013-2014: Intern, Soybean breeding, Coodetec
  - ✓ Hands-on experience in an industry breeding program
- 2011-2015: Undergraduate Research, Plant breeding, Unioeste
  - ✓ Learning in methods of research and development of scientific thought

#### Skills

- Soft Skills: Teamwork, leadership, and communication
- Languages: English and Portuguese
- Quantitative genetics, plant breeding, and genomics
- Computer Skills: R programming (asreml, caret, BGLR) and Python (OpenCV, Keras, Numpy, Pandas)
  - High throughput phenotype: Shovelomics, data acquisition, mosaicking assembly, and data analysis
  - Statistical modeling: Machine learning, mixed models, multivariate models, and Bayesian methods
  - Image processing: RGB, multispectral, thermal, and hyperspectral images

### Additional training

- Workshop on Analysis of Breeding Experiments using ASReml-R (2020)
- Workshop on Crop Growth Models Applied for Plant Breeding (2020)
- Treinamento genotype to phenotype models in plant breeding. (2019)
- System biology and gene networks inference: application to livestock. (2019)
- IV Workshop on Longitudinal and Incomplete Data (2018)
- Quantitative Genetics and Genomics (2018)
- New methodologies for high-resolution mapping and development of molecular (2017)

### **Invited presentations**

- Cultura do Milho: Melhoramento do Milho. Aula da disciplina: Introdução à Engenharia Agronômica. ESALQ. Online. 2021.
- Investigating the genetic architecture of the interaction between tropical maize and plant growth-promoting bacteria via high-throughput phenotyping. Translation Plant Science-Discussion Group (TPS-DG). Virginia Tech. Online. 2021.
- Genetic architecture of the interaction between tropical maize and plant growth-promoting bacteria via high-throughput phenotyping. Genomics and machine learning discussion group. Virginia Tech. Online. 2021.

## Participation in events

- National Association of Plant Breeders 2021 Annual Meeting (Virtual conference)
- International Meeting on Plant Breeding: New approaches on plant breeding: insights into artificial intelligence. 2019 (Meeting)
- 10° Brazilian Plant Breeding Congress. 2019 (Congress)
- 9° Brazilian Plant Breeding Congress. 2017 (Congress)
- II Latin-American Conference on Plant Phenotyping and Phenomics for Plant Breeding. 2017. (Conference).

#### **Publications**

- Galli G, et al. Automated Machine Learning: a case study of genomic "image-based" prediction in maize hybrids. Research Square (Preprint). <a href="https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-840380/v2">https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-840380/v2</a>
- Yassue RM et al. A low-cost greenhouse-based high-throughput phenotyping platform for genetic studies: a case study in maize under inoculation with plant growth-promoting bacteria bioRxiv (Preprint). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456112">https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456112</a>
- Yassue, et al. CV-α: designing validations sets to increase the precision and enable multiple comparison tests in genomic prediction studies. Euphytica. 2021. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.11.11.376343
- Souza, et al. Combining ability for the improvement of vegetable soybean, Agronomy Journal. 2020. https://doi.org/10.1002/agj2.20322
- Espolador, et al. Assessing tolerance to Asian soybean rust in soybean inbred lines from exotic and adapted crosses. Euphytica, 2020. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10681-020-02597-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10681-020-02597-8</a>
- Yassue, et al. Uni and multivariate approaches for diallel analysis in early generation trials for soybean tolerance to rust. Bragantia. 2019. <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/1678-4499.20190037">http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/1678-4499.20190037</a>.